Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain Papers 1775-1913 (bulk 1828-1913)
MSS15503
Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1828-1914.
1,000 items
11 containers
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Union Army officer, educator, and governor of Maine. Correspondence, biographical notes, record books, military reports, speeches, accounts of engagements of the Army of the Potomac, and other material mostly concerning the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brown, John Marshall, 1838-1907--Correspondence.; Burrage, Henry S. (Henry Sweetser), 1837-1926--Correspondence.; Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1828-1914.; Connor, Selden, 1839- --Correspondence.; Hamlin, Charles, 1837-1911--Correspondence.; Howard, O. O. (Oliver Otis), 1830-1909--Correspondence.; McClellan, Carswell, 1835-1892--Correspondence.; Sargent, Horace Binney, 1821-1908--Correspondence.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Warren, G. K. (Gouverneur Kemble), 1830-1882--Correspondence.; Woodman, Cyrus, 1814-1889--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Army of the Potomac.; United States. Army. Corps, 5th (1862-1865); United States. Army. Maine Infantry Regiment, 20th (1862-1865). Company G.
Subjects
Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863.
Places
Maine--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Maine--Militia.; Pennsylvania--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Form/Genre
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.
Occupations
Army officers.; Educators.; Governors--Maine.
Provenance
The papers of Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain, Union Army officer, educator, and governor of Maine, were given to the Library of Congress by Rosamond Allen and Eleanor W. Allen, 1938-1956.
Other Repositories
A collection of Alice Rains Trulock's research materials for her book, In the Hands of Providence: Joshua L. Chamberlain and the American Civil War (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1992), is located at the Pejepscot Historical Society, Brunswick, Maine. These research materials include photocopies of documents from several repositories, including the Manuscript Division.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1828, Sept. 8 Born, Brewer, Maine
1852 Graduated, Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine
1852 1855 Student, Bangor Theological Seminary, Bangor, Maine
1855 Married Fannie Adams
1855 1862 Taught, Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine
1862 Appointed lieutenant colonel, 20th Maine Regiment
1863 Appointed colonel, 20th Maine Regiment Fought at Battle of Gettysburg and awarded Congressional Medal of Honor for his defense of Little Round Top
1864 Promoted by Ulysses S. Grant to brigadier general of volunteers
1867 1871 Governor of Maine
1871 1883 President, Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine
1893 Awarded Medal of Honor for actions at Battle of Gettysburg
1914, Feb. 24 Died, Portland, Maine
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain (1828-1914) span the years 1775-1913, with the bulk from 1828 to 1913. The collection consists of correspondence, biographical notes, record books, military reports, speeches, accounts of engagements of the Army of the Potomac, and other material mostly concerning the Civil War. Included are reports of Company G, 20th Maine Volunteers, and Chamberlain's account of the battle of Gettysburg. There are letters relating to the state militia in Maine, military reunions, and data for a history of the 5th United States Army Corps in which Chamberlain served as a colonel of the 20th Maine Regiment.
Prominent correspondents include John Marshall Brown, Henry S. Burrage, Selden Connor, Charles Hamlin, O. O. Howard, Carswell McClellan, Horace Binney Sargent, William Henry Seward, Gouverneur Kemble Warren, and Cyrus Woodman.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized by type of material and includes an addition.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - 5 Feb. 1848-2 Feb. 1873 (Box 1)
  - 15 Apr. 1873-2 July 1882 (Box 2)
  - 6 July 1882-6 May 1913, undated (Box 3)
- Miscellany (Box 4)
  - Sermon in Philadelphia, Pa., 1775 (Box 4)
  - Prewar and Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine, papers (Box 4)
  - Celebrations Society of the Potomac, 20th Maine Regiment Association (Box 4)
  - Batchelder correspondence (Box 4)
  - Papers as governor of Maine (Box 4)
  - Transition papers, Jan. 1880 (Box 4)
  - Political pieces (Box 4)
  - Letters to his wife (Box 4)
  - Letter to his mother (Box 4)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., and J. E. Rice (Box 4)
  - Reminiscences to Chamberlain (Box 4)
  - Army and Navy Escutcheon Co. (F. H. Dyer) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous postwar correspondence (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous war correspondence (Box 5)
  - Civil War correspondence, original military orders, and mustering out papers (Box 5)
  - Battles, engagements, and skirmishes, regimental records (Box 5)
  - Regimental records, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Regimental records by state, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Regimental records, personnel statistics, and officers? obituary announcements (Box 6)
  - Officers' obituary announcements (Box 6)
  - List of officers (Box 7)
  - Personnel statistics, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Maps (Box 7)
  - Regimental index (Box 8)
  - Reports of operations (Box 8)
  - Dispatches, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Centennial celebration scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Quartermaster's log and Chamberlain's scrapbook of press clippings, 1890s (Box 9)
  - Press clippings (Box 9)
    - Largely 1870s and 1880s (Box 9)
    - Largely 1910s (Box 9)
  - Printed materials by Chamberlain (Box 10)
  - Unbound printed matter, largely annotated (Box 10)
  - Printed matter concerning Chamberlain (Box 10)
- Addition (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1860-1901, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Writings (Box 11)
    - George W. Addams, Paul Parley's Trip to France (Box 11)
    - Horace B. Chamberlain, poem (Box 11)
  - Tracings, sketches, and printed matter (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1889 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence and returns relating to Company G, 20th Maine (Box 11)